A Guide to the Correspondence and subject files of the Director of the Virginia Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation, 1970-2023.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and subject files of the Director of the Virginia Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation,
1970-2023.
The Library of Virginia
34743, 34883, 35466, 39056, 41519, 42374, 42722, 44932, 45393, 51229, 51743, 53856, 54191
Virginia. Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation.
113 cu. ft.; 11 gb
Administrative Information
Arranged alphabetically by subject.
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and other protected information is considered confidential and restricted from public access for 75 years. It may be necessary for an archivist to review any unprocessed, modern record collections (those collections less than 75 years old) that may contain confidential information before the records can be used by patrons for research purposes or before any copies of records can be made for patrons. If you are planning to use these records, please contact Archives Reference Services for more details before planning your research trip.
Acquisition Information
Accession 34743 was transferred by the Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation on 10/25/1994
Accession 51743 was transferred by the Dept. of Professional and Occupation Regulation on 3/1/2016.
Accession 53856 was transferred by the Dept. of Professional and Occupation Regulation on 3/21/2023.
Historical Information
The Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation was formed in 1948 under the Government Reorganization Act. On March 24, 1978, the agency’s name was changed to the Dept. of Commerce. Effective July, 1993, the Department regained its original name. Currently, the Department is responsible for the these Boards: Appraisers (real estate), Architects, Asbestos, Lead and Home Inspectors, Auctioneers, Barbers, Body Piercing, Branch Pilots, Cemetery, Common Interest Community, Contractors, Cosmetology, Fair Housing, Geology, Hearing Aid Specialists, Interior Designers, Land Surveyors, Landscape Architects, Opticians, Polygraph Examiners, Professional Boxing and Wrestling, Professional Engineers, Professional Soil Scientists and Wetland Professionals, Real estate brokers, Surveyor Photogrammetrist, Tattooing, Tradesmen Licensure, Waste Management Facility Operators, and Waterworks and Wastewater Works Operators and Onsite Sewage System Professionals.
The primary function of the Department is to provide administrative support to the boards within the Department which are currently responsible for licensing and certification of occupations. The Boards have regulatory authority for the issuance, suspension and revocation of certificates, permits, and licenses. The Department is operated by a director who is appointed by the Governor. The Department’s activities are broken-down into sub-programs for each of the examining boards. Major activities include review and evaluation of the regulation of professions, examination of those wishing to enter one of the regulated professions, licensing, consumer complaint resolution, and investigation of alleged violations or laws. The mission of the Department of Professional and Occupational Regulation is to protect the health, safety and welfare of Virginians, while promoting a competent workforce, fair housing opportunities, and a productive economy.
Scope and Content
Contains correspondence and subject files of the Director of the Virginia Department of Professional and Occupational Regulation that document the planning, direction, and implementation of agency and board programs and are evidence of actions and policy decisions. Includes correspondence with the agency boards, Secretary of Economic Development/Commerce and Trade, and the Governor’s Office. Also may include newsletters, weekly reports, strategic planning reports, agency study reports, and financial reports.
Accession 51743 consists of the correspondence and subject files of Director Gordon Dixon, who directed the agency from 2011-2014. These records include correspondence, newsletters, various plans and board information. This accession also includes 2 compact disks with correspondence and subject files.
Contents List
- Series I. Director's Correspondence and Subject Files, 1970-2023.
  - Accession 51743 (2008-2014).
    - Board profile summaries, 2014. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 2012-2013. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence - Tracking letters and Appeal letters, 2012. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and subject files - Gordon Dixon - miscellaneous, 2011-2014. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and subject files - Gordon Dixon - compact disks, 2011-2014. (Box 1)
    - DPOR Continuity Plan, 2014 revised. (Box 1)
    - DPOR Transition Manual, 2014. (Box 1)
    - EAGLES Project Quality Plan, 2008 September 26. (Box 1)
    - Newsletters (DPOR Voice), 2010-2013. (Box 1)
  - Accession 53856 (2003-2022).
    - Tracking letters, 2013. (Box 1)
    - Tracking letters, 2014. (Box 1)
    - Tracking letters, 2015. (Box 1)
    - Tracking letters, 2016 Jan. (Box 1)
    - Appeal letters, 2012. (Box 1)
    - Appeal letters, 2014. (Box 1)
    - Appeal letters, 2015. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 2014-2022. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence - Att. Gen., 2003-2004. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence - Auditor of Public Accounts, 2008. (Box 1)
    - Employee recognition, 2008-2010. (Box 1)
    - Newsletters, 2014-2021. (Box 1)
    - Report of financial condition, 2008. (Box 1)
    - Coop certificate, 2005. (Box 1)
    - Delegation of authority, 2006-2010. (Box 1)
    - Fair Housing MOA, 2005. (Box 1)
    - HUD Annual Assessment, 2006. (Box 1)
    - Agency IT Strategic Plan for Budget Approval, 2004. (Box 1)
    - Regulation Revision Report on Audit, 2008. (Box 1)
    - Board appointment letters, 2008-2018. (Box 2)
  - Accession 54191 (2022-2023)., Extent: 11 gb
    Accession 54191 consists of the correspondence of Director Demetrios Melis, 2022-2023 Sept., and is available in electronic format only. Includes Email correspondence, 2022-2023 and Tracking letters, 2023 Feb-Sept, which consist of constituent correspondence, many of which were refered from the Office of the Governor.
    - Tracking letters, 2023 Feb-Sept.
    - Electronic mail, 2022 Jan-2023 Sept.